Frank Esuchenko Papers VHP2005/21
CCSU Veterans History Project
Frank Esuchenko Papers
Bulk, 1944-1946
1944 - 1946, 2005
VHP2005/21
CCSU Veterans History Project
164.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
The collection details experience of Frank Esuchenko during World War II which he served with U.S. Army in the Pacific. Materials in the collection include oral history interview, service records, journal, war time military newspaper, and photographs.
Esuchenko, Frank, 1921 -
Biographical/Historical note
Esuchenko was drafted into the U.S. Army from Bridgeport, CT. He would have preferred the Navy, but he was not given the choice. He went to basic trianing at Camp Claiborne (LA), and then was sent to Okinawa Island. However, he was unable to leave with his original unit, due to an illness, and left later on with a different unit. His job on Okinawa was to maintain the feul tanks and pump stations for the planes that were flying out. Esuchenko describes the island as very beautiful, but it had been mostly destroyed by the battle. For fun the soldiers played baseball and cards, and sometimes were able to see a movie. After the war in Japan ended, he was sent home and discharged.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for Research
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitized and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
Online Access
An online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Technical metadata of digital objects are extracted and encoded in PREMIS preservation metadata format
Preservation Metadata
United States. Army. Engineer Petroleum Distribution Company, 3182nd.; United States. Army.; Fort Dix (N.J.); Interviews; Manuscript; Okinawa-shi (Japan); Photographs; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Japan -- Okinawa Island; World War, 1939-1945 -- Campaigns -- Pacific Area; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American
- Series I: Personal Papers, VHP2005/21.I
  - Order to Report for Induction, Aug. 23, 1944; VHP2005/21.I.1
  - Frank's Journal during his trip back to United States, July - October, 1946; VHP2005/21.I.1I; 45.0 Digital objects
  - Request card for POWs, Branch POW camp #4 Ono-yama, Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.I.3; 45.0
  - Discharge paper, 1946; VHP2005/21.I.4; 45.0
  - Discharge certificate, 1946; VHP2005/21.I.5; 45.0
  - Drawing of Frank Esuchenko, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.I.6; 45.0
  - Okinawa Christmas card, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.I.7; 45.0
  - Seasons Greetings from Okinawa, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.I.8; 45.0
  - A bag from store in Shanghai, China, n.d.; VHP2005/21.I.9; 45.0
  - Separation Document, 1946; VHP2005/21.I.10; 45.0
  - Japanese military currency, 1940s; VHP2005/21.I.11; 40.0 Digital objects
  - Interview synopsis, Nov. 5, 2005; VHP2005/21.I.12; 40.0
- Series II: Publications, VHP2005/21.II
  - The Daily Okinawa, Memorial Edition, Apr. 1, 1946; VHP2005/21.II.1; 4.0 Digital objects
- Series III: Multi-Media, VHP2005/21.III
  - Subseries A: Still Images, VHP2005/21.III
    - Frank Esuchenko's military photo, 1944; VHP2005/21.III.1; 4.0
    - Thanksgiving at Camp Claiborne, LA, Nov. 1944; VHP2005/21.III.2; 4.0
    - Frank Esuchenko, Anna Esuchenko, unknown, unknown (from L - R) Camp Claiborne, LA, 1944; VHP2005/21.III.3; 4.0
    - Ernie Pyle Monument. Shima island, Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.4; 4.0
    - A view of Naha harbor and the depot, where the unloaded equipment is kept. Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.5; 4.0
    - A foundation of a house that was taken down by the Marines. Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.6; 4.0
    - A Japanese temple, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.7; 4.0
    - An Okinawan hut and farmland, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.8; 4.0
    - Village on Okinawa, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.9; 4.0
    - Okinawans in their village getting water from a water well, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.10; 4.0
    - Okinawan engineers, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.11; 4.0
    - View of the end of Okinawa's Pacific side, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.12; 4.0
    - Pacific side of Okinawa, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.13; 4.0
    - Suicide Cliff (where thousands of Japanese commited suicide), Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.14; 4.0
    - Horse carts, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.15; 4.0
    - Japanese plane landing on Shima to talk to General MacArthur of the surrender of Japan. Okinawa., Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.16; 4.0
    - A Japanese hangar being repaired by Americans. Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.17; 4.0
    - A Japanese plane that had been shot down. Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.18; 4.0
    - Pump station. Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.19; 4.0
    - Pump station. Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.20; 4.0
    - Gas station. Naha, Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.21; 4.0
    - Japanese POWs doing work. Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.22; 4.0
    - Rafters on a petroleum tank. Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.23; 4.0
    - Inside petroleum tank being constructed. Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.24; 4.0
    - Building petroleum tanks. Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.25; 4.0
    - Frank Esuchenko(center) building tanks. Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.26; 4.0
    - Frank Esuchenko gauging the petroleum tank. Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.27; 4.0
    - POWs building petroleum tanks. Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.28; 4.0
    - Petroluem tank being constructed, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.29; 4.0
    - Petroleum tank, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.30; 4.0
    - Petroleum tank, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.31; 4.0
    - Bottom of petroleum tank, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.32; 4.0
    - POWs building petrileum tank. Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.33; 4.0
    - Using a jackhammer. Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.34; 4.0
    - Crawford, a crane operator. Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.35; 4.0
    - Crane used to build petroleum tanks. Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.36; 4.0
    - Small bulldozer. Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.37; 4.0
    - Frank Esuchenko with dozer. Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.38; 4.0
    - Frank Esuchenko in front of shed. Okinawa, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.39; 4.0
    - Frank Esuchenko, petroleum tank site. Okinawa, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.40; 4.0
    - Crews, petroleum tank site. Okinawa, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.41; 4.0
    - Supply Corporal Joe Koubek. Okinawa, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.42; 4.0
    - Supply Sgt. A. C. Sonsini. Okinawa, Jan. 20, 1945; VHP2005/21.III.43; 4.0
    - Frank Esuchenko mopping a floor. Okinawa, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.44; 4.0
    - Destruction on Okinawa, Japan, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.45; 4.0
    - After the typhoon, Okinawa, October 9, 1945; VHP2005/21.III.46; 4.0
    - Marine quonset huts, Okinawa, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.47; 4.0
    - What was left of a hangar after a typhoon, Okinawa, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.48; 4.0
    - After typhoon, Okinawa, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.49; 4.0
    - American ship (Landing craft), Okinawa, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.50; 4.0
    - SS John A. Rawlins (Cargo ship) Wrecked in typhoon off Okinawa, 1945; VHP2005/21.III.51; 4.0
    - Cemetery for Marines who died at Okinawa, 1945; VHP2005/21.III.52; 4.0
    - General Simon Boliver Buckner, Jr.'s grave, he led the attack and was killed during the Battle of Okinawa., 1945; VHP2005/21.III.53; 4.0
    - Island Command Cemetery, East China Sea in background. Okinawa, Between 1944 - 1946; VHP2005/21.III.54; 4.0
    - A night picture of V-J night on Okinawa, sky was lit with search lights and bullets, 1945; VHP2005/21.III.55; 4.0
    - Caves on Okinawa, 1953; VHP2005/16.III.56
  - Subseries B: Moving Images, VHP2005/21.IIIb
    - Oral history interview, Nov. 5, 2005; VHP2005/16.IIIb.1; Laczkoski, Jaime (Disk DVD VHP2005/21, Box VHP Interview #1)